Exercise 2-6. Consonant-consonant liaisons. I just didn't get the chance.
I've been late twice. In the preceding examples, you can see that because the
ending st of just and the beginning d of didn't are so near each other in the
mouth, it's not worth the effort to start the sound all over again, so they just
flow into each other. You don't say, I just didn't get the chance, but do say, I
just didn't get the chance. In the same way, it's too much work to say, I've been
late twice. So you say it almost as if it were a single word, I've been late twice.
The sound of th is a special case. It's a floater between areas. The sound is
sometimes created by the tongue popping out from between the teeth and other on
the back of the top teeth, combining with various letters to form a new composite
sound. For instance, S moves forward and the F moves back to meet at the midpoint
between the two. Note, each of the categories in the drawing contains two
labels, voiced and unvoiced. What does that mean? Put your thumb and index
fingers on your throat and say ZZZ. You should feel a vibration from your throat
in your fingers. If you whisper that same sound, you end up with ss and you feel
that your fingers don't vibrate. So, zz is a voiced sound, ss unvoiced. The
consonants in the two left columns are paired like that. B P D T V P G C G G Z Z
Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z Z er, mmm, mmm, mmm, yeh, wah.